Héctor Climente González

Computational biologist & machine learning researcher

Paris, France +33 7 68 13 20 39 https://hclimente.eu https://github.com/hclimente

ABOUT ME

"Learn only to be content" – Inscription in Ryōan-ji, Kyōto.

The driving forces of my life are learning and personal growth. I strongly believe in multidisciplinarity and collaboration and created synergies by combining engineering and basic research, biology and machine learning, academia and the private sector.

SELECTED WORK EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral researcher

MAY 2020 - NOW

RIKEN AIP

▶ Development of feature selection methods for biological data (GWAS and transcriptome), with emphasis on biological networks and detection of interactions.

Doctoral researcher

OCT 2016 - APR 2020

Institut Curie & Mines Paris Tech

- ▶ Development of feature selection methods for high dimensional datasets, with emphasis on biological networks.
- ▶ Application of the aforementioned methods to biomarker discovery in GWAS datasets, both single-SNP and epistasis.
- ▶ R package *martini* published in Bioconductor, and Python packages *pyHSICLasso* and *spada* in PyPI.
- ▶ Conducted internships in Liège University and RIKEN AIP.

Research assistant

DEC 2013 - AUG 2016

Pompeu Fabra University

- ▶ Large-scale analysis of the involvement of alternative splicing in cancer.
- ▶ Integration of multi-omics data.

Head of Biocomputing

SEP 2014 - MAY 2015

Anaxomics Biotech Ltd.

- Development and maintenance of pipelines for the statistical treatment of omics data.
- ▶ Supervision of intern, and collaboration with IT and Data analysis departments regarding database and software maintenance and product deployment.

EDUCATION

2016 – 2020 Ph.D. in Bioinformatics
Paris Sciences & Lettres Univ.

2012 – 2014 M.Sc. in Bioinformatics
GPA 9/10

Pompeu Fabra University

2010 – 2013 **B.Sc. in Biochemistry**GPA 8.74/10, 1st Class Honors *Barcelona Autonomous Univ.*

2008 – 2012 B.Sc. in Biotechnology

GPA 8.58/10

Barcelona Autonomous Univ.

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Co-author of 10 articles, cited over 400 times.

Climente-González et al. (2020). Boosting GWAS using biological networks: a study on susceptibility to familial breast cancer. PLoS Comp Bio, 17 (3)

Climente-González et al. (2019). Block HSIC Lasso: model-free biomarker detection for ultra-high dimensional data. *Bioinformatics*, 35 (15), i427–i435.

Climente-González *et al.* (2017). The functional impact of alternative splicing in cancer. *Cell reports*, 20 (9), 2215-2226.

SELECTED AWARDS

2020 Special Postdoc. Researcher

RIKEN

2016 – 2019 **PhD EU Fellowship**

MSCA COFUND

LANGUAGES

spanish Native

ENGLISH Fluent

FRENCH Intermediate

Japanese Beginner

TECHNICAL SKILLS

PROGRAMMING Python, R, C++, Bash

PYTHON pytorch, numpy, pandas, scikit-learn

R tidyverse, igraph, Rcpp

BIG DATA nextflow, HPC (PBS Torque, Slurm),

SQL, Jupyter

OMICS GWAS, RNA-Seq (single cell and bulk),

MS-MS proteomics

ML/STATISTICS Graph regularization, statistical

interactions, nonlinear association

deep learning

DEVOPS Docker, conda, unit testing, continuous

integration, git

SOFT SKILLS

- Experienced **communicator**: talks in international conferences, lead writer of articles and grant proposals, imparted workshops on reproducible research.
- ▶ **Project management** in teams and singleperson projects, **mentoring**, and coordination of **international collaborations**.
- ▶ **Organization** of summer school on breast cancer, **teaching** assistant in large scale machine learning course.
- Courses on critical thinking, ethics, project management, theater, and mindfulness.